<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bitcoin | Thoughts & Technical Writings.]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/blog/categories/bitcoin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-17T22:15:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Campbell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mecampbell25@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bitcoin the Freedom Fighter]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/2017/02/17/bitcoin-the-freedom-fighter/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-17T21:36:41-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/2017/02/17/bitcoin-the-freedom-fighter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Bitcoin represents a mental stepping stone, a philosophical spring board from which I&rsquo;m better able to envision a future not controlled by the State and its numerous appendages (the FBI, CIA) and countless subsidiaries. By breaking the link between money and sovereignty (there are neither Presidents nor sovereigns printed on bitcoins), Bitcoin paves the way for a tidal wave of cultural, social, and technological innovation and progress. Since Bitcoin offers an Internet of Money with no inherent overlap with existing (i.e. fiat) monetary and financial systems, over time as adoption rises, people will be motivated to keep an ever-increasing proportion of their value in Bitcoins <strong>because it is better money.</strong> This last point is not debatable; it is not an opinion, it is not fake news, it is fact. Fiat money is not yours (aside from cash; but what portion of your value do you hold in cash?) - it is merely an IOU, a ledger balance. When you log into your online banking (assuming you live in one of the advanced economies where we have access to such financial services), the money that you see and claim to &ldquo;have in your account&rdquo; has in reality been lent out or applied to some probably more risky strategy like trading or financing of some exotic, complicated deal loaded with tantalizing fees for the bankers involved. If - or rather, when, given the history of financial crises, which seem to be part of the human economic condition - there is a run on the bank and the FDIC, you will be forced to get in line with all the rest (and probably take a massive haircut, i.e you will lose most or all of the money held in bank accounts).</p>

<p>This is simply not the case with Bitcoin. You <strong><em>are</em></strong> your bank. Bitcoin is strictly a bearer asset, where possession of the private key that allows your coins to be spent is ten-tenths of the law, so to speak.</p>

<blockquote><p>But, bitcoins are not very useful today. I have to wait at least 20 minutes for my transactions to be confirmed; transaction fees are too high, I pay nothing to use my credit cards. Why would <em>anyone ever use Bitcoin</em>?</p></blockquote>

<p>Ask the people in Africa, South America, East Asia, and so on, where each morning you wake up and hope that your grab bag of problems created by Big Brother doesn&rsquo;t have a surprise waiting for you. That list includes things like profound corruption &amp; graft, the social strangehold wraught by nepotism at all levels of socieyt, hyperinflation of your currency that destroys your purchasing power on a daily basis, oppressive political regimes which rob &amp; pillage the people, and so on.</p>

<p>If, 10 years ago before Bitcoin was invented, someone has asked you the following question, how would you have responded?</p>

<blockquote><p>How long would it take to design an Internet of Money which is not controlled by any central arbiter, no government, no corporation; a freely accessible network that cuts out the banks and turns the global financial-monetary system on its head and renders it utterly useless?</p></blockquote>

<p>I suspect you&rsquo;d either laugh, stare, or walk away, thinking something like, &ldquo;Dreamers, who needs &lsquo;em.&rdquo; We all would have. Bitcoin has existed for 8 short years and it&rsquo;s already significantly better than SWIFT, ACH, and most bank transfer services around the world.</p>

<p>In 10 years, maybe 5, all the &ldquo;problems&rdquo; that exist today with Bitcoin will be solved. Lightning Network is coming, SegWit will be adopted, and the impact of Bitcoin&rsquo;s open, permissionsless protocol allowing for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n2yD1PSWBU0">exponential innovation</a> will render all the world&rsquo;s fiat currencies laughably, hopelessly obsolete with no shot of ever catching up. From there, the virtuous cycle of utility begetting adoption <em>ad infinitum</em> will kick in, and then it&rsquo;s simply game over for the incumbents.</p>

<p>So, what happens to things like taxes when, in the future, everyone is storing their value in Bitcoin, where it <a href="http://www.libertylifetrail.com/2016/04/04/the-top-use-cases-for-bitcoin/">is easy to hide it from the prying eyes of the State and even your spouse</a>? It will trigger a forced revolution, a painful, messy, chaotic breaking with the past - a cultural &amp; social forest fire which will wipe out the old guard and the incumbents, anyone standing in the way of progress, and will give the future over to the nerds and to the Individual. Power structures like governments will no longer be able to domineer over their &ldquo;subjects&rdquo; by dictating and controlling what they can (buy things at Wal-Mart, please!) and cannot (that politician is evil, and since you donated to her you must be, too!) do with your money. The State and any centralized entity will only be able to grow as large as the exact number of Individuals which explicitly &ldquo;vote&rdquo; to support that structure, where voting is represented as financial support - buying a product from a company, paying for a service, donations, or even paying taxes if you&rsquo;d like.</p>

<p>The future is bright for the Individual, but the transition will be difficult. And we really haven&rsquo;t even begun yet. Remember: <a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/the-law-of-accelerating-returns">all exponential relationships appear to be linear at the beginning</a>. I hope I live long enough to see the revolution in full swing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bitcoin and taxes (your favorite topic!)]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/2016/11/25/bitcoin-and-taxes/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-25T12:18:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/2016/11/25/bitcoin-and-taxes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Each $5,000 of annual tax payments made over a 40-year period reduces your net worth by $2.2 million assuming a 10% annual return on your investments,&rdquo; reports James Dale Davidson in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Sovereign-Individual-Transition-Information/dp/0684832720"><em>The Sovereign Individual: Mastering the Transition to the Information Age</em></a></p></blockquote>

<p>Just let that sink in for a bit please. Mull over the figures in your delicate psyche. Imagine the impact of &#36;2.2mm on your future.</p>

<p>&hellip; now, who&rsquo;s ready to talk about taxes?!</p>

<h3>Is Bitcoin useful for tax evasion?</h3>

<p><small>(<strong>NOTE</strong>: This is not tax advice, nor am I suggesting you seek to evade paying taxes. This post is for entertainment purposes only.)</small></p>

<p>There are two types of taxation regimes the world over: You either live in a country with <strong>competent</strong> or <strong>incompetent</strong> tax authorities.</p>

<p>If incompetent, there are a dozen other ways to avoid paying taxes, probably all of them easier than Bitcoin.</p>

<p>The United States is certainly one of the more competent tax collectors in the world via its &lsquo;revenue&rsquo; (talk about a euphemism) arm, the IRS.</p>

<p>So our question is really: is it possible to use bitcoin for tax evasion within the US?</p>

<h3>What can the IRS <em>do</em>, exactly?</h3>

<p>As of today, the IRS simply <a href="https://bitcoinmagazine.com/articles/tax-day-is-coming-a-primer-on-bitcoin-and-taxes-1459786613">hopes that you report any capital gains on profits obtained on net BTC purchases</a>. However, it&rsquo;s clear the IRS is trying to move from &lsquo;hope&rsquo; to &lsquo;coerce&rsquo; as its policy verb of choice: they&rsquo;ve <a href="http://www.coindesk.com/irs-seeking-data-coinbases-bitcoin-customers/">just asked for a broad and sweeping disclosure from Coinbase</a> regarding its customers&#8217; historical transaction data. Should this data be handed over to the Feds, you can bet they will start building a ledger for each customer - purchases made (volume and price) net of sales (again, volume and price) and send you a capital gains bill for any PNL realized on those transactions.</p>

<p>However, this doesn&rsquo;t address situations in which you&rsquo;ve used Coinbase (or another exchange like <a href="https://gemini.com/">Gemini</a>) solely to purchase your coins, and immediately withdrawn them to your personal, private wallet.</p>

<p>What will the IRS&#8217; policy be regarding these murky situations? Remember, I&rsquo;m saying &lsquo;murky&rsquo; here because <strong>they do not know the fate of your withdrawn bitcoins</strong>. That means that you could have:</p>

<ul>
<li>lost your coins -> you&rsquo;d claim a capital <strong>loss</strong> in this case, since the capital you outlaid upfront is now worth exactly $0</li>
<li>held onto your coins -> you&rsquo;d report nothing as you only incur capital gains upon <em>sale</em> of your investment</li>
<li>sold your coins -> you&rsquo;re supposed to report this honestly and pay capital gains</li>
</ul>


<p>As you can see, the main issue here for the IRS is their <strong>total and utter lack of transparency</strong>. Bitcoin does not need the IRS&#8217; nor the Federal government&rsquo;s blessing to exist - it just does. It is a completely separate, autonomous payment network that is under the control of no single individual or entity. There is no one rubber-stamping transactions like the Federal Reserve does in this country.</p>

<p>Some open questions, however, remain regarding the extent to which the IRS could pursue an individual (i.e. audit them) if they suspect misreporting of capital gains/losses regarding cryptocurrency holdings. Will they conduct rigorous <a href="http://www.coindesk.com/what-block-chain-analysis-tells-bitcoin/">blockchain analysis</a> - which is extremely computationally expensive (by design, in a way&hellip; more on this in another post perhaps) - to try and piece together a story and send you a tax bill? This strategy is feasible in theory, but would represent a huge consumption of their resources in practice.</p>

<p>The fact is that the tools at the disposal of the IRS are limited at best.</p>

<p>Perhaps, though, this is for the better.</p>

<h2>A better tax regime</h2>

<p>In bitcoin, you pay taxes on every transaction - it&rsquo;s called the transaction fee. You can <em>voluntarily</em> pay a higher fee and you will increase the likelihood that your (probably time-sensitive) transaction will be part of the network&rsquo;s next block, i.e. your transaction will be settled in a much more timely manner. This is an example of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voluntary_taxation">voluntary tax system</a> (credit to <a href="https://twitter.com/TravisPatron">@TravisPatron</a> for <a href="http://www.coindesk.com/why-bitcoin-creates-a-voluntary-tax-system/">exposing me to this concept</a>).</p>

<blockquote><p>[The Bitcoin] transactions queue represents a voluntary, pay-for-performance taxation structure where the performance derived from the system is dependent upon how much taxation [a user is willing to] pay.</p></blockquote>

<p>Bitcoin puts the power back in the hands of its users. If you value the service, the right to use the Bitcoin network to move value between two nodes in the network, then you pay tax for that performance.</p>

<p>Imagine a system where you pay tax for roads only when you use the roads to drive. Or you only pay taxes to schools in the form of some tuition cost when your children are attending those schools.</p>

<p>I think that a tax regime that aligns a person&rsquo;s tax liabilities with his or her <em>behaviors</em>  (where a behavior is an expression of their preference) is a compelling vision for the future. Perhaps you will agree.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WorldWideWebCoin: A Thought Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/2016/10/26/world-wide-web-coin-a-thought-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-26T14:18:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/2016/10/26/world-wide-web-coin-a-thought-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><sub>
<em>WorldWideWebCoin - WWWCoin vs. Bitcoin - More usefulness leads to more adoption leads to more usefulness</em>
</sub></p>

<p>Bitcoin is <a href="https://www.coinbase.com/what-is-bitcoin?locale=en">many things</a> - open source peer-to-peer (p2p) digital money; an <a href="http://fortune.com/2016/10/18/winklevoss-state-street-bitcoin-etf-administrator/">alternative asset class for investors</a>; and possibly the global reserve currency of the future, when <a href="https://startupboy.com/2014/04/01/the-fifth-protocol/">machines are participating in marketplaces autonomously without human intervention</a>.</p>

<p>The value of one Bitcoin (1 BTC) in essence is a reflection of its <strong>usefulness</strong> across the many functions in which it&rsquo;s being used.</p>

<p>Bitcoin starts to look more like a safe haven asset that&rsquo;s decorrelated with, say, the S&amp;P500? Its value should increase.</p>

<p>Bitcoin can be used more and more places to buy goods and services? Its value should increase.</p>

<p>More companies offer employees compensation partially of wholly in Bitcoin? Its value should increase.</p>

<h2>WWWCoin Hypothetical Price History</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say there had been a <strong>WWWCoin</strong> back in 1994 shortly after Tim Burners-Lee <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Wide_Web">invented the World Wide Web</a> in the late 1980s.</p>

<p>Now picture a chart of that coin&rsquo;s valuation from its inception in c. 1989; through the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dot-com_bubble">dot-com bubble&rsquo;s bursting</a> beginning in 2000; and finally bring it through to the present. What would that chart look like? Here&rsquo;s my take&hellip;</p>

<div style="text-align:center">
<img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/k30yfttch1o54yl/Screenshot%202016-10-26%2016.24.53.png?dl=1"/>
</div>


<h2>Bitcoin Realized Price History</h2>

<p>Just for fun, let&rsquo;s see how our hypothetical WWWCoin chart compares to the realized BTC price chart to date.</p>

<div style="text-align:center">
<img src="https://www.dropbox.com/s/d5ukaisoi2f194n/Screenshot%202016-10-26%2015.29.20.png?dl=1"/>
</div>


<p>Some similarities of note:</p>

<ul>
<li>Early precipitous rise leads to a bubble, i.e. overdone price increase relative to the <strong>actual + potential usefulness of both the internet and Bitcoin</strong></li>
<li>Steady, grinding recovery following the first major crash in price as <strong>the technology continues to make strides in terms of usefulness and applicability</strong></li>
<li><strong>No clear upper bound on price as usefulness enters into a virtuous feedback loop</strong> - more adoption means more usefulness means more adoption, ad nauseam.</li>
</ul>


<p>The last point has only been realized to date in the case of the Internet; my prediction is Bitcoin will follow a similar pattern. Have you heard of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Micropayment">micropayments</a>? The technology that will finally <a href="https://medium.com/on-blendle/in-a-world-of-ad-blockers-we-need-micropayments-9ddb2f6793cf#.cn7bn57v8">kill YouTube ads</a>? Well, they&rsquo;re almost here, courtesy of Bitcoin and the <a href="https://lightning.network/">Lightning Network</a>.</p>

<p>I think we&rsquo;re standing on the precipice of an inflection point in Bitcoin&rsquo;s history - at which the feedback between Bitcoin&rsquo;s expanding utility and increasing price becomes obvious to just about everyone. Do you want to participate or not?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
