<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: lambda | Thoughts & Technical Writings.]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/blog/categories/lambda/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-04T14:52:07-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Campbell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mecampbell25@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Lambdas as Computed Hashes in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattcampbell.nyc/2015/06/18/using-lambdas-as-computed-hashes-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T11:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattcampbell.nyc/2015/06/18/using-lambdas-as-computed-hashes-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently read a <a href="http://blog.honeybadger.io/using-lambdas-in-ruby">blurgh post</a> about the interesting, quirky aspects of lambdas in Ruby.</p>

<p>One feature that stood out to me was lambdas&#8217; ability to stand in where hashes would normally be used.</p>

<p>This functionality is made possible because, in Ruby, lambdas can be called in any of the following ways:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">l = lambda { |x| puts x }

l.call("Foo") =&gt; "Foo"
l.("Foo")     =&gt; "Foo" (admittedly this syntax is bizarre to me...)
l["Foo"]      =&gt; "Foo" (looks like hash access using the typical Hash#[] method...)
</code></pre>

<p>The third way is the bridge between lambdas and the concept of &ldquo;computed hashes&rdquo;. I searched for a definition of computed hash, but didn&rsquo;t find much consensus. The working definition for this post would be something like:</p>

<blockquote><p>A hash object whose values can be initialized (read: computed) at runtime based on logic declared elsewhere in the program.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Putting It Together: An Example</h2>

<p>When might the use of computed hashes, i.e. lambdas, be a favorable replacement to a normal hash?</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you&rsquo;re writing tests for your program and you want to add a degree of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuzz_testing">&ldquo;fuzz testing&rdquo;</a>. As an example, perhaps one of your classes is initialized with <code>first_name</code> and <code>last_name</code> attributes (note the <code>initialize</code> method expects to receive a <code>Hash</code>-like argument as input in sticking with Rails convention), and then generates a <code>slug</code> to be used for query string parameters elsewhere in your application:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">class Person
  attr_reader :first_name, :last_name

  def initialize(hash_like_object = {})
    @first_name = hash_like_object[:first_name]
    @last_name  = hash_like_object[:last_name]
  end

  def slug
    @slug ||= "#{first_name.downcase[0, 3]}-#{last_name.downcase[0, 3]}"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now let&rsquo;s generate an instance of the <code>Person</code> class to make sure everything looks OK:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; matt = Person.new(first_name: "Matt", last_name: "Campbell")
#&lt;Person:0x007fca00179bd0 @first_name="Matt", @last_name="Campbell"&gt;
ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; matt.slug
"mat-cam"
</code></pre>

<p>This checks out. Our <code>slug</code> method is pretty dumb, but let&rsquo;s say it becomes more complex: we amend <code>slug</code> to handle duplicates. As it stands, &ldquo;Arthur MacCormack&rdquo; and &ldquo;Art MacNulty&rdquo; will have the same slug and so are not uniquely identifiable by their slug.</p>

<p>The point of interest here is NOT the logic you end up implementing to make <code>slug</code> more unique. What&rsquo;s of interest is how you can fuzz test whatever logic you end up implementing throughout your test suite.</p>

<h3>Faker + Computed Hash = Fuzz Testing</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/stympy/faker">Faker</a> is a great library for generating random data, which I most typically use in conjunction with <a href="https://github.com/thoughtbot/factory_girl">FactoryGirl</a> to generate instances of my models (that is, the Ruby classes that represent the domain I&rsquo;m modelling in the application).</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see how we can utilize a computed hash to improve the degree of fuzz testing in my unit tests:</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">require 'faker'

# Here is the Person class definition again for reference.

class Person
  attr_reader :first_name, :last_name

  def initialize(hash_like_object = {})
    # The next two lines work because our hash-like-object, in some cases a lambda,
    # can be called using the same [] syntax as Hash#[]
    @first_name = hash_like_object[:first_name]
    @last_name  = hash_like_object[:last_name]
  end

  def slug
    @slug ||= "#{first_name.downcase[0, 3]}-#{last_name.downcase[0, 3]}"
  end
end
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="ruby"># Construct our computed hash lambda...

randomizer = lambda { |k| Faker::Name.send(k) }
</code></pre>

<p>And, voilà, we can initialize <code>Person</code> instances using our <code>randomizer</code> (which is in fact a lambda, and not a hash):</p>

<pre><code class="ruby">ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; person = Person.new(randomizer)
#&lt;Person:0x007f81f0dfc8b0 @first_name="Nedra", @last_name="Pouros"&gt;
ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; person.first_name
"Nedra"
ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; person.last_name
"Pouros"
ruby-2.2.2-p95 (main):0 &gt; person.slug
"ned-pou"
</code></pre>

<h2>tl;dr</h2>

<p>Need to generate pseudo-random instances of your classes in order to utilize fuzz testing across your test suite? Try initializing your instances using a computed hash, which in Ruby can be implemented using a lambda and <code>call</code>-ing it using the hash accessor <code>Hash#[]</code> that you&rsquo;re used to seeing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
